<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true and perfect declaration of the mighty army by the sea made and prepared by the generall states of the vnited prouinces, purposely sent forth to hinder the proceedings of the King of Spaine, vnder the conduct of Peter Vander Does generall of the said army: together with all whatsoeuer hath bene done by the said army against the islands, townes, castels, and shippes, belonging to the said King of Spaine. As also what the said army hath gotten and wonne in the said viage; with the whole discourse of the aduentures of the said army, both in their going forth, and retuning againe, from the 28. of May, 1599. vntill the 6. of March, 1600. Collected by Ellert de Ionghe, captayne of the artillery in the said viage.</title>
            <author>Jonghe, Ellert de.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1600</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 74 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04630</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14750</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119662</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854869</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854869</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20324</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04630)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20324)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 472:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true and perfect declaration of the mighty army by the sea made and prepared by the generall states of the vnited prouinces, purposely sent forth to hinder the proceedings of the King of Spaine, vnder the conduct of Peter Vander Does generall of the said army: together with all whatsoeuer hath bene done by the said army against the islands, townes, castels, and shippes, belonging to the said King of Spaine. As also what the said army hath gotten and wonne in the said viage; with the whole discourse of the aduentures of the said army, both in their going forth, and retuning againe, from the 28. of May, 1599. vntill the 6. of March, 1600. Collected by Ellert de Ionghe, captayne of the artillery in the said viage.</title>
                  <author>Jonghe, Ellert de.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By [S. Stafford for] Iohn Wolfe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1600.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Actual printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20324:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20324:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE True and perfect de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the mighty army by ſea, <hi>made and prepared by the generall States of the</hi> vnited Prouinces, purpoſely ſent forth to hinder the proceedings of the King of Spaine, vnder the conduct of <hi>Peter Vander Does</hi> Generall of the ſaid army:</p>
            <p>Together with all whatſoeuer hath bene done by the ſaid army againſt the Iſlands, Townes, Caſtels, and Shippes, belonging to <hi>the ſaid King of Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As alſo what the ſaid army hath gotten and wonne <hi>in the ſaid viage; with the whole diſcourſe of</hi> the aduentures of the ſaid army, both in their going forth, and returning againe, from the 28. of May, 1599. vntill <hi>the</hi> 6. <hi>of March,</hi> 1600.</p>
            <p>Collected by <hi>Ellert de Ionghe,</hi> Captayne of the Artillery in the ſaid Viage.</p>
            <p>Printed at London by Iohn Wolfe. 1600.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:20324:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:20324:2"/>
            <head>The true and perfect declaration of <hi>the mighty Nauy by Sea, prepared &amp; ſet forth</hi> by the States of the vnited Prouinces (to hinder the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of the king of Spaine) vnder the leading and conduct of <hi>Peter Vander Does,</hi> Generall of the ſaid Nauy, ſhewing what the ſaid army hath done againſt the Iſla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, Townes, Caſtels, and ſhips of the ſaid king, with the riches and prizes by them taken and gotten during their whole viage: as alſo what the ſaid army hath performed by Sea, as wel in their viage outward, as homeward. From the 28. of May 1599. to the 6. of March 1600. gathered &amp; col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by <hi>Elbert de Ioughe,</hi> Captaine of the Artillery in the ſaid Nauy.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Pon the 28. of May 1599. The States ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my put to ſea, out of Zealand, being in all 73. ſhippes, holding their courſe between Calis and Douer, the wind being Eaſt Northeaſt.</p>
            <p>The 29. of May, hauing paſt Calis, with an Eaſt wind, &amp; cleare weather, in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uening they had a calme, then the Generall caſt ancker vnder Swartnes, which done, all the nauy did the like.</p>
            <p>The 30. of May, hauing hoyſed anker, they ſet ſayle with a North Northweſt wind, keeping vpon the coaſt of England, and about twelue of the clock, they paſſed Beueſide, the wind being Eaſt Northeaſt, they holding their courſe Weſt South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt, being cloſe weather, which cauſed the Generall to ſayle Weſtward, the better to haue the coaſt of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in ſight, but all the day continued cloſe weather, yet in the euening they had a ſight of Goutſtaert, and ſo ſayling til night, they ankered not farre from Plimmouth.</p>
            <p>The 1. of Iune early in the morning, making towards land, about ſixe of the clocke they arriued at Plimmouth, where the Generall ſent a Pinace to land, to know if any of their ſhips
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20324:3"/>
had arriued there, becauſe certaine of them had ſailed out of the Taſſel not long before, which they thought to haue found at Plimmouth: but not finding any, about noone they ſet ſaile &amp; departed, holding their courſe South Southweſt: &amp; about e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uening hauing a ſide wind, they ſailed Weſt Southweſt, with ſuch darke &amp; cloſe weather, that they could hardly ſee y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of a ſhip from them, which cauſed them ſometimes to ſhoot off muskets, ſomtimes ſlings, to let the other ſhips know that they were not farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they ſhould not ſeparate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues.</p>
            <p>The 2. of Iune, hauing a calme with cloſe weather, they met al together, and holding their courſe South ſouthweſt, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the wind Eaſt Northeaſt.</p>
            <p>The 3. of Iune, ſtill hauing an Eaſt Northeaſt wind, they ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led very ſlowly ſometimes on the lee, ſometimes in the wind, to ſtay for certaine of their ſhips that were ſomewhat behind, and in the end being all together, the Generall held his courſe South ſouthweſt, all the Nauy following him, in the night ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a Southweſt wind.</p>
            <p>The 4. of Iune, the General put forth 2. flags, &amp; ſhot off two peeces, for a ſigne to call all the Captaines &amp; Maſters, to come aboord of his ſhip, there to hold a Marſhall aſſembly, which was preſently performed, each of them putting foorth their boates, to boord him, hauing as then paſt Heyſſant about ten miles, with a Southweſt wind, running South ſoutheaſt: and in the euening hauing a Southeaſt wind, all the Nauy held their courſe South ſouthweſt.</p>
            <p>The 5. &amp; 6. of Iune, it was calme with great clappes of thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ſailing then vnder 47. degrees.</p>
            <p>The 7. of Iune, they had a Weſt wind, whereupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the whole Nauy ſet their courſe South ſouthweſt: after that, the wind co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming North, they ſailed Southweſt, yet very ſlowly, by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſome of the ſhips were ſo far behind, that they could hardly be diſcerned, whereupon the reſt of the ſhips ſtaied for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: at the ſame time the Generall made an order for the diuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their meat, euery 6. men to haue amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 5. li. of biſquit for a day.</p>
            <p>The 8. of Iune, ſtill hauing a Weſt wind, they held their
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20324:3"/>
courſe South ſouthweſt: and about euening the wind falling ſomewhat ſharpe, the whole Nauy woond about: then the wind co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming Weſt againe, they were conſtrained to abate ſome of their ſayles.</p>
            <p>The ninth of Iune, they eſpied the coaſt of Galiſia, as then hauing a North-weſt wind, holding their courſe South-weſt, and about three of the clocke in the after noone, the whole nauie hauing turned about, &amp; made to ſea-ward, not lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g after they made towards the land again: but being too low from <hi>La Corougie,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> General cauſed the whole Nauie to put to ſea again.</p>
            <p>The tenth of Iune, the Nauie ſailing again towards the land, they had a South-weſt wind, and in the euening a Northweſt wind, wherwith they ſayled weſt, being not far from the land.</p>
            <p>The eleuenth of Iune, earlie in the morning, the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie making towards the ſhore, &amp; being vnder the land, percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing themſelues to be as high as the Corougie, they ſet their courſe Weſt South-weſt, the wind being Eaſt North-eaſt, &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout noone came before the Corougie: where being come, and ſtaying for three of their ſhips that were behind, which were the ſhips of <hi>Cornelis Clauſ.</hi> Captaine <hi>Ianſ.</hi> and a Pinace: In the meane time they made all the preparation they could, and about one of the clocke ſpreading all their ſayles, they put into the heauen, all together caſting anker, very neere within the ſhot of the town: wherupon thoſe of the Corougie ſhot di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers great peeces at the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: which dangerous ankering the nauie well perceiuing, and finding no conuenient place to land their men, about 5. a clocke in the euening they hoyſed anker: which the town perceiuing, began to ſhoot more fiercely, but did not any hurt vnto the ſhips. The ankers being vp, there fell ſuch a calme, that the ſhippes were in great daunger, for that the towne ſhot vpon them ſo mightily, although they could not reach them, and the ſhippes by reaſon of the calme, not well to be ſtered, that they had much paine and labour to hold them from the land, and the towne ſhot ſo mightily, that in a ſhort ſpace they had ſhotte at the leaſt aboue two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and thirtie ſhot, and yet could they not reach the ſhips,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20324:4"/>
although it ſeemed vnpoſsible, for that the ſhips, by reaſon of the calme, were driuen ſo neere vnder the towne, that they might haue ſhot into them with a musket: and the Generals ſhip was driuen ſo neere to the towne, that Captaine <hi>Rem E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarts,</hi> and brother <hi>Ianſon,</hi> with their Pinnaces were forced to go and help him: yet in the end with great danger the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy got to Sea.</p>
            <p>The 12. of Iune, in the morning being ſomewhat diſtant from the land, the ſhips draue before the calme.</p>
            <p>The 13. of Iune, in the morning about 9. of the clocke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the cape <hi>Finiſterre,</hi> they had a Northeaſt wind.</p>
            <p>The 14. of Iune, hauing a ſtiffe Northwind, they held their courſe South, and South &amp; by Eaſt, and the wind continuing, in the euening they tooke in all their ſayles, letting the ſhips driue before the wind without ſailes.</p>
            <p>The 15. of Iune, the wind leſſening, they began to hoyſe ſailes, holding their courſe Southeaſt, &amp; the wind ſtill continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing North, about 9. of the clocke in the morning, they diſcried cape <hi>Roxent,</hi> &amp; therewith they made towards the land, purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to do ſome exploit vpon Lisbon, but in the euening, the whole Nauy woond about, holding their courſe South, South-weſt.</p>
            <p>The 16. of Iune, in the morning the wind being North, they held their courſe South Southweſt, &amp; about the ſame time, the Admirall <hi>Iohn Garbrantſ.</hi> put forth a flagge in his ſterne, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring to haue certaine Pinnaces, that were vnder his quarter, to come on board of his ſhip: but none went aboard, but kept with the whole fleet to Leeward.</p>
            <p>The 17. of Iune, hauing a Weſt wind, they ſet their courſe South Southweſt, and about euening they perceiued among their fleet a ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſhip, &amp; a barke with three baſes, wherupon preſently the Generall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded 4. of the beſt ſhips of ſaile in the whole Nauy to make chaſe after them: which ſhips ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing taken the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, brought them before the General, who hauing ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with them, in the end they departed friendly from each other, for it was an Engliſhma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. About that time Captaine Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20324:4"/>
ſhip loſt the fleete, by reaſon that the fleete in the night time changed their courſe, and woond about.</p>
            <p>The 18. of Iune, the Nauie driuing before a calme, the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall put forth his accuſtomed token, to call all the captaines and maſters aboard his ſhip, there to conſult with him.</p>
            <p>The 19. of Iune, ſtill hauing a calme, with a South-winde, order was taken by the Generall, for the landing of certaine men, whenſoeuer they approached any coaſt.</p>
            <p>The 20. of Iune they had a calme, and helde their courſe South South-weſt.</p>
            <p>The 21. &amp; 22. of Iune, hauing a good ſwift forewind, they held their courſe South South-weſt, at which time the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall cauſed the whole Nauie to bee aduertiſed, that euerie man ſhould behaue and rule himſelfe, according to the Articles in that caſe prouided, and eſpecially following the 41. and 42. Articles, the contents whereof do follow.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="articles">
                        <head>NOTA.</head>
                        <p>Whoſoeuer without ſpecial cauſe, &amp; that firſt made known vnto his officers, ſhal breake out of his array, where he ſhal be appoynted to abide, or that ſhall ſeeme to flie out of any bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile or enterpriſe, whether it be before a towne or otherwiſe, he ſhall and may preſently bee ſlaine or ſtabbed by any man whatſoeuer; &amp; being take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and impriſoned, ſhal be proclaimed traitour, and in that caſe puniſhed with death, without any fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour.</p>
                        <p>Any man being placed and ſet to defend any fort, ſconſe, or trench, whether hee be captaine or ſouldiour, eyther by wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or by land, ſhall defend and keepe the ſame, to the laſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie, both with words and workes, not doing any thing to the contrarie, whereby the ſame ſhould be loſt without extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, vpon paine of death, without fauour or exception.</p>
                        <p>No man muſt giue himſelfe to take any ſpoyle, without charge or commiſsion, vpon paine of death.</p>
                        <p>Hereunto adding, that no man ſhould venture or be ſo bold to defile or deflowre any maide or woman whatſoeuer, vpon paine of death.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="8" facs="tcp:20324:5"/>It was likewiſe commaunded by the Generall, that no man ſhould kill or murther any woman or children, (vnleſſe they were found in armes to reſiſt) vpon paine of death.</p>
                        <p>Alſo it was determined by the Generall, and the reſt of the Captaines, the better to encourage the ſouldiours, as alſo for other cauſes and reſpects, that what priſoner ſoeuer ſhould be taken, able to pay a good ranſome, the tenth part of the ſaid ranſome ſhould be giuen to the ſaylers and ſouldiours, the reſt to him that tooke him priſoner.</p>
                        <p>Alſo that when they determined to aſſaile the firſt Caſtle or fort, they ſhould cauſe a pike with a fane to bee ſet vp vpon the land, and as long as the fane ſtirred with the wind, they ſhould ceaſe from ſhooting out of the ſhips againſt the fort or Caſtle.</p>
                        <p>The like token ſhould be ſet vp before a towne, when they would not ſhoote any more againſt it.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>The 23. of Iune, hauing a good fore-wind out of the North, they held their courſe South South-weſt, ſending out a pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace to ſeeke for land, for that as then they were of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on not to be farre from it, which pinnace about euening retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned backe againe.</p>
            <p>The 24. of Iune, ſtill hauing a North winde, they held their courſe South ſouth-weſt, and the ſunne being South-eaſt, they ſent out three pinnaces to diſcrie la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, at which time the Vice-admirall of the red flag put forth another flagge, deſiring cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine captaines to come board his ſhip, whereof ſome boar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him, &amp; about ſix of the clocke in the euening they diſcried la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, wherunto they made, holding their courſe Eaſt ſoutheaſt.</p>
            <p>The 25. of Iune, in the morning very earlie, they were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Lanſerottes,</hi> and then held their courſe South South-weſt and by Weſt, and in the euening diſcryed the Iſland of great Canaria, keeping the whole night vnder the Iſland.</p>
            <p>The 26. of Iune, in the morning very early being cloſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Iſland, they made to the ſhore, meane time making preparation to land their men in ſmall boates, approaching neere vnto the Caſtle, yet without danger of their ſhotte,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20324:5"/>
they of the caſtle began to ſhoot, but the Hollanders eſteemed not thereof, but to the contrarie went ſo cloſe vnto the Caſtle, that they might reach it with a musket.</p>
            <p>Vnder the Caſtle there lay three Spaniſh ſhips, whereof the greateſt was by the Hollanders ſhot vnder water and ſunke.</p>
            <p>The Caſtle ſhot hard againſt the Hollanders, and the ſhips in like ſort againſt the Caſtle, eſpecially out of the Generals ſhip, as alſo out of many of the other ſhippes, in ſuch ſort, that the Iſland ſeemed to be compaſſed about with fire: during the which ſhooting, the ſouldiours were put into ſmall boates, and ſo rowed to land.</p>
            <p>The Spaniards vpon the downes neere the ſhore, had cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine baſes, wherewith they ſhot hard vpon the Hollanders boates, at their entring vpon the land, but the Hollanders ſtayed with their boates, being readie to land: for it was ſo appoynted, that not any man ſhould ſeeme to ſet foote on land, but muſt ſtay hard by the Generall: alſo that not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them ſhould ſpread any colours, before hee ſhould bee landed, and yet they muſt not doe it, before the Generall ſhould bee on ſhore, who onely had an enſigne in his Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace. Thoſe of Zealand and North-Holland were appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to land towardes the Towne, and thoſe of Amſterdam, and of the Maze, towards the Caſtle, and all at one time. The Caſtle perceiuing ſo many boates manned, beganne to ſhoote ſlowly, for that the Captaine of the Caſtle made his ſouldiours beleeue, that they had not aboue halfe a barrell of powder left, whereupon they left off ſhooting: whereat the Spaniards that lay in the downes, beganne to flie, and then all the boates that lay ready manned, rowed to land.</p>
            <p>Firſt the Generalles boate: which being cloſe by the ſhore, the Spaniards perceiuing, to (let him from landing) skip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped into the water vp to the chin, againſt the Generals boate, and fought ſo boldly with the Hollanders, that the Generall himſelfe ſtanding valiantly in the boate fighting, and ready to leape on the ſhore, was in the end forced to returne, and the Spaniards made ſo hot an aſſault, that a Captaine ſtanding by
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20324:6"/>
the Generall, was thruſt into the arme, but diuers of the Spaniards were ſhot, ſo that in the end not many remained to make reſiſtance.</p>
            <p>With that the Generall valiantly leaped into the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vp to the middle: and after him followed <hi>Albert Ianſen</hi> Cox enſigne, who hauing ſpred his colours, all the reſt of the boates rowed to land, hauing giuen a great vale of ſhotte againſt the Caſtle. The ſouldiours being landed, and ſtanding in order of battaile, being about foure thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men, the Generall cauſed <hi>Dammas Verloo,</hi> one that could ſpeake good Spaniſh, to aske them of the Caſtle, if they would yeelde it vp: and hauing parled for the ſpace of an houre, in the meane time the Generall ſette vp a vane vpon a pike, to warne the ſhippes not to ſhoote againſt the Caſtle; which ſhooting preſently ceaſed: and being in parle, in the end they of the Caſtle agreed to deliuer it vp, vpon condition, that the Spaniards ſhould depart without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny armes, which was preſently done. In the which Caſtle the Generall placed Captaine <hi>Iohn Allertſ.</hi> of Amſterdam, who entring into it, found therein fifteene great braſſe pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and ſixe Iron peeces, well prouided with powder and munition, being ſo ſtrong, that in a manner it was impregnable: the walks beeing at the leaſt thirtie foote thicke.</p>
            <p>Captaine <hi>Iohn Allertſ.</hi> with his companie being placed ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and the Spaniards to the number of ſixtie perſons gone out, the Hollanders ſouldiours being about foure thouſand ſtrong, marched towardes the towne: but by the way, being come to a valley not aboue a quarter of a mile from the towne, they ſtayed all night vntill the morning: in the meane time diuers companies of the ſouldiours marched to the towne, &amp; went ſo cloſe vnder the walles, that they ſpent the whole night in skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhing with the enemie, ſpecially the company of <hi>Dammas Verloo,</hi> where hee loſt many of his men.</p>
            <p>The twentie ſeuenth of Iune, in the morning, their enſignes wauing in the wind, they marched towards the towne: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20324:6"/>
within Cannon ſhot of the Caſtle, that ſtood before the towne, the Caſtle ſhot mightily vpon the Hollanders, and ſpoyled many of their men, for they could not faile one ſhotte: for although they could hardly ſee the Hollanders, yet they ſhotte at the enſignes: whereby the Hollanders were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to march ſomewhat aſide to ſhunne their ſhot: which was eaſie to be done, being round about co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſed with downes: but the ſouldiours ſtayed cloſe vnder the walles of the towne, where they ſtood out of danger of the enemies ſhotte, for that the downes were ſo great, that they might eaſily defend themſelues from the ſhot.</p>
            <p>The Hollanders in that ſort keeping themſelues cloſe, the enemie ſuppoſed that they were in minde to retire backe againe; ſo that beeing before fled out of the Towne, they returned into it againe, (as it was certified vnto the Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders) to reſiſt them, and to that end placed Ordinance vpon the hil, that lay vpon the right hand of the way vnto the ſhore, wherewith they did much hurt vnto the Hollanders, for that from the ſayd hill they ſhot many of their men, and likewiſe ſhotte mightily from the Caſtle with diuers woodden bullets, which did much miſchiefe.</p>
            <p>The Generall perceiuing no meanes to winne the Towne, vnleſſe ſome great ſhotte were planted before it (for they from the hill ſhotte ſo hard, as alſo from the Caſtle, who for the want of Iron bullets, ſhotte bullets of Tinne and Lead, that no good on his ſide could bee done) vſed all the ſpeede that might bee, to plant a batterie, and to place Ordinance before the Towne. Whereupon ſending for the great peeces that lay in the Caſtle that Captaine <hi>Iohn Allertſ.</hi> kept, placed as many of them as they could before the Towne, not without very great labour and paine: for that many times the peeces beeing drawne halfe way forward, brake their carriages, whereby that day they could bring but three peeces before the Towne, whereof two were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted to ſhoote towards the hill, and therewith, (although very high to ſhoote vp) draue the Spaniards to ſuch a poynt,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20324:7"/>
that they left ſhooting, not daring to ſtand cloſe together, as they did before the Hollanders planted their Ordinance: and when the Hollanders were drawing the peeces towardes the towne, many times ſhot ſome of their men. The Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers, hauing ſhot eight times, did likewiſe ceaſe; meane time preparing their batterie, in the night placing two De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie Cannons among their batterie: but in the meane time the Spaniards conuayed all their goods and treaſure out of the town, not many men remaining within it, perceiuing that the Hollanders minded to winne it by force; ſo that they conuey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all their goods vpon the hilles.</p>
            <p>The twentie eight of Iune, earlie in the morning, the two demy Cannons being placed in batterie againſt the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, Captaine <hi>Rem Euartſon</hi> was appoynted with his ſhippe to ſayle before the Towne, and to ſhoote at it, and they on land battered the Caſtle, with two peeces of Artillerie.</p>
            <p>Meane time there were three demy Cannons more pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in batterie, which were likewiſe appoynted to batter the Caſtle, ſo that as then they beat it with fiue peeces toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Then they ſent two companies of ſouldiours vpon the hill, who as then had a right path vnto the towne, the one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the companie of <hi>Monſieur Meerkercke,</hi> the other of Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell <hi>Stoem,</hi> the companie of <hi>Damas Verloo</hi> compaſsing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath about the foote of the hill.</p>
            <p>In this ſort the Generall battered the Caſtle with fiue peeces, ſo that in the end the Spaniards within the Caſtle forſooke it, and fled, after that the Hollanders had diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged fortie foure times vpon it: which the Generall percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, preſently ſent a companie of men into it, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſette fire vpon the Towne gate, thereby to make paſſage for the Souldiours to enter: but while the gate burnt, the Saylors could by no meanes enter into the Towne.</p>
            <p>But the two companies of Souldiours that went vp the hill, had a right path vnto the Towne, as alſo the companie of <hi>Damas Verloo,</hi> that compaſſed about the foote of the hill:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20324:7"/>
but the Saylors could not enter before the fire was ceaſſed and the gate emptied, for that the Spaniards had filled the gate with ſtones vp to the middle: but the Generall behaued himſelfe ſo valiantly, that hee cauſed certaine companies with lathers to ſcale the walles, he himſelfe in perſon entering with them: in the meane time, the three companies from the hill with their colours diſplaid, marched towards the towne, and entering, went into the market place, where they ſtayed to ſee if any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance would be made. The fire at the gate being quenched, and the ſtones borne away, the troupe of Amſterdam were appointed to bring 4. demy Cannons into the towne, which they muſt do before that any of them ſhould enter; which was ſpeedily performed, euery man being very diligent to worke, that they might enter into the towne, hoping to get great ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, each man thinking to do his beſt, but all in vayne, for the Spaniards had conuayed all their goods out of the towne.</p>
            <p>While the Demy cannons were drawing into the towne, there came a Saylor being of Fluſhing, out of the towne, who for the ſpace of fiue yeeres had beene kept therein the holy houſe, who perceiuing <hi>Cornelis Leinſen</hi> Admirall of the Zeala<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſhips, and for that he knew him, he fel downe at his feet, calling him his deliuerer (next vnder God) out of priſon, wherein he had remained for the ſpace of 5. yeeres: which done, hee was led before the Generall.</p>
            <p>The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of Soldiers being entred into the Caſtle, they found in it 5. great peeces of ordinaunce.</p>
            <p>The ordinance being brought into the towne, &amp; the troupe of Amſterdam, whoſe Coronell was <hi>Cornelis Remmiſen,</hi> hauing vnder him 3. companies of Saylors, being entered, after him followed the troupe of Zeala<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, with the troupe of the Maze in Holland. Whereof one part being entered, they were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to ſtay in a plaine field, vntill the Generall had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed euery man his quarter: wherby it was very late, before the Captaines entered into their quarters, where they found the houſes empty, except it were here and there ſome women: for the Spaniards were all fled away with their goods.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:20324:8"/>The 29. of Iune, hauing throughly ſearched throughout the towne, &amp; not finding any man, the General cauſed certain co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of Souldiers to preſent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues before the caſtle that ſtood vpon the South ſide of the towne, &amp; to ſommon them to yeeld: but when they approched it, they found no man within it. Which done, one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany entred, wherein they left 20. ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, and in it they found 3. great peeces of ordinance, but all ſtopped with nailes, ſtones and other ſuch like things, to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnſeruiceable. The reſt of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panies ree<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tered the towne. This caſtle ſtood about the length of a Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>non ſhot ſouthward without the towne, being very ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, for that the one ſide ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſtood in the water, ſo that in a manner it was inuincible.</p>
            <p>But God, in whoſe power all conqueſts conſiſt, had ſtric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Spaniards hearts with feare, for it was not wonne by force: for aſſure your ſelues, if they had holden the firſt caſtle, it would haue beene a very daungerous way to haue paſſed to the towne: and againe the caſtle that ſtood vpon the ſtrand, where the ſhips entered, could ſhoote croſſewiſe one from the other, ſo that not any man could haue paſſed without great danger. God be praiſed for this victory.</p>
            <p>But to returne againe vnto the matter, the company of ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers being reentered, in the euening the Generall ſent 10. ſaylors of Captaine <hi>Harman Michtelſ.</hi> company, &amp; 10. of Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Rem Euartſ.</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany their enſigne, being lieutena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the ſaid captaine <hi>Rem Euartſ.</hi> and euery night they were releeued, for that they lay therein in great dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, becauſe the Spaniards might eaſily haue hidden themſelues in the vineyards, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conuenient time either in the entry or iſſuing of the Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers, might haue cut them off. For that (as it is ſaid before) the caſtle ſtood a Cannon ſhot from the towne.</p>
            <p>The 30. of Iune, there was a parle with the Spaniards touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ranſoming of the towne, or els to ſuffer it to be burnt: the Spaniard would giue no money, but proffered the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall to furniſh his whole Nauy with ſufficient wine, ſaying that they had no money, wherewith they departed for that time, not effecting any thing.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:20324:8"/>The 1. of Iuly, the word of God was preached within the towne of great Canaria, in S. Annes Church, where there aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled great nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of ſaylors &amp; ſouldiers, as alſo the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, with al his Marſhal cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell &amp; other Captaines: the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers text being taken out of the 103. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> the people ſinging the 100. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> thanking and praiſing God for the victory, all with one conſent calling vpon the name of the Lord.</p>
            <p>The 2. of Iuly, a Marſhall court was holden to puniſh two malefactors, whoſe ſentence was to be hanged.</p>
            <p>The 3. of Iuly, the malefactors were brought forth to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; being in the market place, one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had his pardon, the other was hanged: at the ſame time there was a ſmall mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſouldiers, being deſirous to chaſe the enemy that had fled vp into the hilles with their goods, yet no man made the Generall acquainted therewith.</p>
            <p>This murmuring ſtill continuing, the Generall was content to permit 6. companies to go vp vpon the hilles, to chaſe the enemy, the companies being Captaine <hi>Iohn Lambertſen Hoy,</hi> Captaine <hi>Iochem Hendrickſ. Swarten hondt,</hi> Captaine <hi>Cornelis Claeſen:</hi> the Enſigne being <hi>Claes Corneliſen,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelis Claeſen,</hi> captaine <hi>Knooper,</hi> captaine <hi>Quack,</hi> and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of captaine <hi>Moye Iaques</hi> of Rotterdam, which companies vpon the hill loſt many of their men, moſt dying by reaſon of the great heat, ſome of them went aſide to winne ſome pray, but before they could be releeued, many of them were ſlaine by the enemy: in this fury was ſlaine captaine <hi>Moye Iaques</hi> of Rotterdam.</p>
            <p>Coronel <hi>Cornelis Remmiſen,</hi> with the company of Captaine <hi>Rem Euartſ.</hi> and Captaine <hi>Harman Michelſen,</hi> had the reare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, but were conſtrained to retire backe with loſſe of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their men, being ſent forth in the hoteſt time of the day, and about euening returned backe againe, without doing any exploite.</p>
            <p>The 4. of Iuly, the Holla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders with their colours diſplaied iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued out of the towne, who by the Generals co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſet it on fire in diuers places, taking with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al the great ſhot, bels, &amp;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20324:9"/>
whatſoeuer the Spaniards had left behind them, but great ſhot was the beſt prize that was found within Canaria: for they found in the Iſland of Canaria 19. braſſe, and 6. yron peeces, which were all lade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboord the ſhips, without any hurt, or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune to any man.</p>
            <p>The 6. of Iuly, the Generall put forth two flags, for a ſigne that all the Captaines, and Maſters ſhould go aboord his ſhip, that he might conſult with them.</p>
            <p>Where it was ordeined, that each Captaine either of Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers or Sailers, ſhould bring forth all the prizes, that they had gotten in the Iſland of great Canaria, &amp; that vpon their oath.</p>
            <p>And that the ſame goods whether it were victuals, drink, or any other thing, ſhould by the Purſers of euery ſhip, together with an officer of the Souldiers, and one of the Saylers, be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtred, and by them openly ſold, alwaies prouided that no Souldier ſhould beſtow more then the value of one moneths pay, vnles the Captaine gaue his word, or bought it with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy money.</p>
            <p>That the victuals and drinke ſhould not be ſold, but onely regiſtred; and whoſoeuer ſhould be found, to haue concealed any thing, ſhould be puniſhed according to the contents of the article in that caſe prouided; and further, to be diſmiſſed of his part of the prizes taken, as alſo that ſhould be taken during the whole viage.</p>
            <p>Each Prouoſt, or any other perſon, that ſhould haue intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of any ſuch concealed goods, or that could name any man that had concealed any thing, the ſaid Prouoſt, or other perſon, ſhould haue the one halfe thereof, the other halfe to be kept, for the vſe &amp; commodity of wounded men in that viage, whether they be Souldiers or Saylers.</p>
            <p>Each Purſer ſhould keepe a perfect regiſter of all the goods found within their ſhips, how much they were ſold for, which they ſhould deliuer vnto the principall Secretary, to the end that the monies proceeding thereof, might be iuſtly and truly imployed to the vſe and benefit of the whole army. It was to be vnderſtood, that all the goods ſold at that time, ſhould be
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20324:9"/>
brought forth, and that the buiers thereof ſhould ſeeke their warrants of the ſellers.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>The great ſhot found in the firſt Castle.</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>li.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>dz.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>One braſſe peece, waighing</cell>
                     <cell>6833.</cell>
                     <cell>17.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>one braſſe peece waighing</cell>
                     <cell>4254.</cell>
                     <cell>17.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>one peece</cell>
                     <cell>4142.</cell>
                     <cell>17.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>one braſſe peece w.</cell>
                     <cell>6961.</cell>
                     <cell>17.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>one braſſe peece w.</cell>
                     <cell>2162.</cell>
                     <cell>6.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>one braſſe peece w.</cell>
                     <cell>4500.</cell>
                     <cell>38.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>one braſſe peece w.</cell>
                     <cell>2115.</cell>
                     <cell>6.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>one braſſe peece w.</cell>
                     <cell>4450.</cell>
                     <cell>17.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>one braſſe peece waighing</cell>
                     <cell>4780.</cell>
                     <cell>40.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>More, as they entred, they found vpon the ſtrand one field peece waighing about 2100. pound, with 2. baſſes of braſſe.</cell>
                     <cell cols="2">all 40197. li.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>Great ſhot found in the ſecond Castle on the North ſide of the Towne.</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>li.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>One braſſe peece waighing</cell>
                     <cell>6772</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>one braſse peece w.</cell>
                     <cell>1800</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>one braſse peece w.</cell>
                     <cell>4254</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>one braſse peece w.</cell>
                     <cell>3506</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>one braſse peece w.</cell>
                     <cell>1680</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Found vpon a hill a field peece and two baſses of braſse</cell>
                     <cell>1400</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>17412</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>Great ſhot found in the caſtle on the Southſide of the Towne.</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>li.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>One braſse peece waighing</cell>
                     <cell>6068</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>one braſse peece w.</cell>
                     <cell>4653</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>one braſse peece w.</cell>
                     <cell>1377</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>and ſome bullets.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>12098</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo all the belles, which they tooke with them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:20324:10"/>They likewiſe ſunke a ſhip lying before the firſt caſtle, that lay to be laden for the weſt Indies: there was alſo an other Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh barke, which they tooke with them, &amp; of all the great ſhot taken in Canaria, one peece was ſunke, &amp; by captaine <hi>Bankes</hi> meanes, there was an other braſſe peece left on ſhore.</p>
            <p>There was other goods brought aboord the ſhip (which by the Generals commaundement) was ſold before the maſt of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſhip. They had in the towne 140. pipes of wine, and a great number of pottes of oyle. The men they loſt in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naria were 1440. dead, and 60. wounded.</p>
            <p>The 6. of Iuly, the Generall commaunded captaine <hi>Ruyts</hi> ſhip of Rotterdam to be vnrigged, becauſe it had a great leake, and was wholy vnſeruiceable, which being on land was burnt, and in ſtead thereof rigged a barke by them taken in Canaria, wherein captaine <hi>Ruyt</hi> put his men, and was one of them that was appointed for the longer viage.</p>
            <p>The 7. of Iuly, lying ſtill before Canaria, the townes-men came forth with a flagge of peace, deſiring to redeeme ſome of the priſoners, for the enemy had taken 4. of the Hollanders, who vpon the 3. of Iuly were left vpon the hill, ſicke &amp; wholy vnable to trauell: &amp; it appeareth that one of thoſe 4. priſoners came from a Spaniard that had his ſonne priſoner in the ſhip called the Orange, wherein the Generall himſelfe ſayled, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one of them that went out of the caſtle. But vpon delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, anſwere was made them, that they ſhould returne againe the next day.</p>
            <p>The 8. of Iuly, very early they came againe vnto the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, ſhewing him that the principall of the towne had taken their priſoners from them, as it was true. For the Spaniards would not agree to any ranſome.</p>
            <p>Then the Spaniards that were priſoners, being about 60. perſons, were deuided into diuers ſhips: which done, the Nauy put to ſea, from the North end of the Iſland of Canaria, with a Northeaſt wind, and in the euening caſt anker againe vnder the South end of the Iſland.</p>
            <p>The 9. of Iuly, being yet vnder the South end of the Iſland
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20324:10"/>
of Canaria, many of their me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beſtowed their time in lading of freſh water, &amp; wherſoeuer they went on ſhore, burnt al before them. The ſame day the Generall made a ſigne, that all the Purſers ſhould go aboord his ſhip, there to deliuer the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the goods that were ſold, which they deliuered vnto <hi>Wieringhen</hi> the Generals Secretary.</p>
            <p>The 10. of Iuly, they ſet ſaile from off the South end of great Canaria, hauing calme weather, and variable ayre, but in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uening they had a ſtiffe wind out of the Northeaſt, wherewith they held their courſe Weſt Southweſt, &amp; by night the wind being high, they were conſtrained to take in their Marſſailes, &amp; to runne Northweſt, holding their courſe to <hi>Teneriffa,</hi> min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to do ſome exploite vpon <hi>Geracico,</hi> but not long after, they altered their mindes.</p>
            <p>The 11. &amp; 12. of Iuly, hauing ſtrange &amp; hard weather, they vſed all the meanes they could to get to <hi>Gommera,</hi> the wind be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as then North Northeaſt, with foule weather.</p>
            <p>The 13. of Iuly, hauing calme weather, they yet ſought to get vnder <hi>Gommera,</hi> which they did, about 12. of the clocke at noone: with that the Generall put forth his accuſtomed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, to call all the Captaines and Maſters aboord his ſhippe, where it was agreed to ſend three companies of ſouldiers into a creeke, there to take land, which was about halfe a mile from the towne, which companies ſhould march ouer the hilles, &amp; they in the meane time with the whole Nauy would vſe all the diligence they could to get before the towne, which they did: the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panies being gone, the Nauy made towards the towne, where being come, they prepared themſelues to land the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, which with great diligence was done.</p>
            <p>Now lying at ancker before the towne, preſently the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers and ſaylers were put into the ſmall boates, attending a ſigne from the Generall.</p>
            <p>Then the Generall putting forth his colours, all together at one inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t they rowed to ſhore, which was done with great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition, they of the towne not once making any reſiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: but as they of Canaria did flee vp into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tains, not leauing any
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20324:11"/>
thing behind them, and whatſoeuer they could not carry, they hid it ſo well that it could hardly be found.</p>
            <p>The companies of ſouldiers &amp; ſaylers being on land, &amp; Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinels placed, the 3. companies that were ſent ouer the hilles came vnto them, who had ſent 20. muskettiers out of each co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, (to ſee if the Spaniards would make any reſiſtance) who deſcending downe the hill, perceiued certaine Aſses laden by the Spaniards, which they made after, thinking to get a good prize, &amp; to be the lighter left all their muskets: which the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards that lay hidden in the vineyards perceiuing, left their ambuſtadoes, and comming forth ſlewe them all: in this ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw there were 58. ſlaine, who being dead the Spaniards ſtripped off all their clothes, &amp; went away with the pray. In the meane time the three companies hauing loſt 60. or at the leaſt 58 men, entered into the towne.</p>
            <p>The 14. of Iuly, by great labour &amp; paines taken in digging, the Hollanders found 8. pipes of wine within the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, which were preſently laden in the Captaines ſhips that were appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the longer viage, the pipe valued at 7. pound Flemiſh: meane time many of the ſaylers brought freſh water aboord, the better to be prouided in their viage.</p>
            <p>The 15. of Iuly, being yet buſied to lade water and other balaſt, they found two Demy cannons, which the Spaniards had buried in the earth.</p>
            <p>The 16. of Iuly, in the morning, the Generall put forth his accuſtomed tokens, to call the Captaines &amp; Maſters aboord his ſhip, where it was agreed, that the ſhips appointed for the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger viage, ſhould be prouided as need required, and that they ſhould take out of the ſhips appointed to returne againe into Holland, as much victuals as the ſaid ſhippes could well ſpare: which was done, and preſently thereupon laded all the wheat and rie out of the one ſhips into the others, againſt they ſhould haue neede to bake it, for the preſeruation of their liues, if the viage happened to be long.</p>
            <p>It was alſo concluded, that all the companies of ſouldiers ſhould marche vp the hilles, to chaſe the enemy: meane time
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:20324:11"/>
the ſaylers ſhould ſtay within the towne.</p>
            <p>So vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the 17. of Iuly, in the morning about 2. houres before day, with a ſtill drum they marched vp, hauing very cold and fine weather, but returned againe the ſame day, not doing any exployt: which done, the ſaylers were ſent on board the ſhips.</p>
            <p>The 18. of Iuly, vſing great diligence in digging, they found another demy cannon and two belles.</p>
            <p>The 19. of Iuly, all the ſouldiours being ſhipped, the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall gaue commandement to ſette the towne on fire: and at that preſent the ſouldiours were deuided and placed in the ſhips that ſhould goe the longer viage.</p>
            <p>The 20. of Iuly, the Generall put foorth his accuſtomed ſignes, to call all the Captains and maſters aboord his ſhippe, where the ſhippes that ſhould goe the longer viage, were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted, ſeparated, and made readie to ſet ſayle.</p>
            <p>The 21. of Iuly, all the Nauie put to ſayle from Gommera, hauing the winde North-weaſt, and being ſomewhat off from the land, departed from each other, the ſhippes for the long viage being in all 34.</p>
            <p>The ſhips appoynted to returne to Holland, vſed all the meanes they could to paſſe betweene Teneriffa and Gomme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, being in number 37. ſhippes great and ſmall: but percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing it to bee impoſsible to paſſe betweene the Iſlandes, for that beeing there it blue ſo ſtiffe, that they could hardly beare any ſayle: they ſtroue to paſſe betweene Palma and Gommera, which they likewiſe could not paſſe, ſo that the 22.23. and 24. dayes of Iuly, they kept thereabouts: at that time the Admirall <hi>Iohn Garbritſ.</hi> the Vice-admirall <hi>Logier Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſen,</hi> and the ſcout <hi>Cornelis Clauſen,</hi> with moſt of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, ſeparated themſelues from the reſt of the ſhippes.</p>
            <p>The 25. of Iuly, holding their courſe South and by weſt, they were vnder 21. degrees.</p>
            <p>The 26. of Iuly, they held their courſe South and by weſt, with little winde, the wind being North-eaſt and by eaſt, with a good pleaſing gale.</p>
            <p>The 27. of Iuly, the allowance of bread among the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:20324:12"/>
was abated, becauſe they ſuppoſed the viage would be longer then it fell out.</p>
            <p>The 28.29. and 30. of Iuly, their courſe beeing South-weſt, and by Weſt, the wind North-weſt, the Captaines and Maſters went all aboord the Generals ſhip, which dayes they miſt the ſhippes of Brother <hi>Ianſen,</hi> becauſe it had ſayled forward, and the reſt of the ſhips changed their courſe: and the ſame day likewiſe, they diſcryed the Iſland of Saint <hi>Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las,</hi> being from them South-weſt and by weſt.</p>
            <p>The 31. of Iuly in the morning, they were right vnder the Iſland, and had almoſt ſayled round about it, becauſe they could finde no anker ground, ſo that they lette their boates ſayle cloſe vnder the Iſland to ſeeke a road, where they found two roades, wherein all the ſhippes might lie, about a Coluerin ſhot diſtant from the land, and twelue fadome water, and there ſtood three houſes.</p>
            <p>The firſt of Auguſt, they diſcryed the Iſland of Saint <hi>Luce,</hi> diſtant from them Weſt north-weſt: all that day they ſtayed by the Iſland of Saint <hi>Nicholas,</hi> and with their Pinna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces went on land, to ſee if they might finde freſh water for their Nauie, but they found not any. There they ſaw ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie great Torteauxes, whereof they tooke one that weighed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt three hundred pound. The ſame day all the Captaines and Maſters met on boord the Generall, to take counſell whether they ſhould ſayle to get freſh water: at laſt it was concluded to ſayle to <hi>Iſola de Maio,</hi> where certain of their ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lops went on land for freſh water: but by reaſon of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable heate of the ground, they loſt ſeuenteene men, and certaine of their ſhalops ouerturned.</p>
            <p>The ſecond of Auguſt, they helde their courſe South-eaſt and by eaſt, with a calme all the day long.</p>
            <p>The third of Auguſt in the morning, they diſcryed the Iſland of Saint <hi>Iames:</hi> and the ſame day they took a Torteaux, hauing at the leaſt fiue hundred egges in her belly, a hundred and fiftie of them hauing ſhelles, the reſt without ſhelles, as hennes vſe to haue in their bodies, beeing very great, as big as
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:20324:12"/>
a ball of a ſtiuer; with the which egges they made tanſeyes, which taſted very well: of the fleſh of the Torteaux, they made hodge-podge, and it taſted like bacon. The egges that were ſhelled, had ſhelles like winde-egges, wherewith they played at tennis aboord the ſhips, which rebounded like a tennis ball, and you muſt ſtrike very hard with them before they would breake.</p>
            <p>The fourth of Auguſt in the morning they made towardes the land, and about noone ankered vnder the Iſland <hi>de Maio,</hi> where Generall went on ſhore, and there ſtayed till the next day at noone.</p>
            <p>The fift of Auguſt, there came a ſhippe vnto them, that had beene vnder fiue degrees Northward of the Equinoctiall line, to ſayle to Braſilia, and was conſtrayned, hauing a leake, to put to the ſhore with them, beeing a Venetian. The Captaines name was <hi>Antonie Bolorio;</hi> the ſhippe was laden at <hi>Calis Malis,</hi> with wine, oyle, and other goods: which ſhippe and goods hee auouched to bee his, but it was found to bee contrarie, for that the Marchant beeing a Spaniard, was there preſent, meaning to ſell their wares at Braſilia, ſo that both the goods and Marchant were found good prize; and the Captaine with his ſhippe and thirtie Pipes of wine for his neceſſarie prouiſion, let depart, becauſe hee was a Venetian, balaſing his ſhippe with certaine pipes of ſalt-water.</p>
            <p>The ſame day they ſent out a Pinnace, with a man of warre, beeing of Zealand, to chaſe a ſhippe that they e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpied: which ſhippe beeing taken, was found to bee a Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingall, laden in Porta Port, with wine, oyle, linnen-cloath, Silkes and Veluets, which amounted vnto (as the Captaine of the ſaide ſhippe teſtified vnto them) 20000 duckets.</p>
            <p>The tenth of Auguſt, they put to ſea againe, to meete the Portingall with their two ſhippes that went to chaſe him, for that the prize was ſo euill of ſayle, that it could not make to them, but by night both ſhee and their two ſhippes came
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:20324:13"/>
among the fleet: and at that time alſo brother <hi>Ianſens</hi> ſhippe, which had beene miſsing thirteene dayes, came likewiſe to the fleete.</p>
            <p>The 11. of Auguſt, they returned again vnto the rode, from whence the day before they had departed, where they began to vnlade their prize, which by their Marſhal court was fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d lawfull; the ſhip and goods both being forfeit: the ſhip had in it eight Iron peeces.</p>
            <p>The 12. of Auguſt, there boorded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> foure men out of the Iſland <hi>de Maio,</hi> ſhewing them that in the Iſland there dwelt no more but foure Moores, &amp; fiue white men: in the Iſland were very faire horſes, that ranne about the country, and great hennes, that went as faſt as a dog, and being weary with going, flew away: they are commonly taken by night in the trees, and thouſands of goates.</p>
            <p>The 15. of Auguſt, the blacke dog, &amp; <hi>Albert Ianſ.</hi> returned again vnto them as they lay at anker, bringing with them two Spaniſh barkes, each hauing three baſes in them, the one vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laden, wherein they put diuers priſoners, and let them ſayle to Saint Iacobs: the other was laden with cotten wooll, and came from <hi>Ciuill:</hi> they brought likewiſe a ſhip of <hi>Marſellis,</hi> of 100. tunnes, laden with wine and oyle.</p>
            <p>The ſame day there came vnto them two Netherland ſhips, which ſet ſayle out of the Weelings, hauing bene fiue weekes and a halfe vpon their viage, they brought them newes that the enemie was gone to lie three miles from Bommel, and that being vnder Goutſtrat, they ſpake with three of the ſhips that went for the Eaſt Indies, and with them was a pinnace, all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Amſterdam, very richly Iaden: the two Netherland ſhips were ſayling to the weſt Indies for ſalt.</p>
            <p>The ſame day they put to ſayle, and departed from the Iſland <hi>de Maio,</hi> holding their courſe South South-eaſt: the winde Northeaſt, with a good gale of winde. The ſame night the barke taken by the blacke dogge, loſt both her maine maſt, and her forke maſt.</p>
            <p>The 21. of Auguſt, holding their courſe South-eaſt, with a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20324:13"/>
good gale of wind, in the night time they loſt one of their Purſers, he was ſick, but no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> knew what was become of him.</p>
            <p>The 31. of Auguſt, in the morning, they fell cloſe vpon the land of Gommera, by a high peece of ground reaching into the ſea, which is called Cape de Monta, where they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kered, about three ſmall miles from the land, at ſixteene fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome water, where, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the one ſide of the ſhip they fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the water to be freſh, &amp; on the other ſide ſalt, &amp; Eaſt and by ſouth from them, they ſaw a great riuer, all the coaſt of the land be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing full of trees; the riuer was called Rio Noua.</p>
            <p>The 1. of Septe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, they fetched freſh water out of the riuer.</p>
            <p>The fift of September, the Generall entered into a Riuer, called Rio de Puntes, where they found about thirtie wilde men, moſt of them naked, and amongſt them was their kings ſonne, who ſtayed alone with them in the Generalles pinnace for the ſpace of an houre: hee brought them a tinne veſſell full of ſodden rice, with two ſodden hennes, and the Generall gaue him a potte of twelue gallons of wine, and a boxe of Marmalade.</p>
            <p>The 6. of September, they put to ſea, and that day eight Cannoes of wilde men made towards their ſhips, ſome with three, and ſome with foure men in a Cannoe, whereof ſome boorded their ſhippes: they held their courſe that day South ſouth-eaſt.</p>
            <p>The tenth of September in the morning, they diſcryed the Cape de los Palmos.</p>
            <p>The 11. of September, to the 19. they draue vpon the ſea with calme weather: in the which time all the Captains &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters conſulted with the Generall, about the landing of the Iſland of Saint Thomas, with 1400. men.</p>
            <p>The 22. of September in the morning, they diſcried the Iſland of S. Thomas, being South and by weſt from them.</p>
            <p>The 23. of September, they held their courſe Eaſtward, not to be diſcouered by thoſe of the Iſland, being of opinion, that they could not enter into the roade: ſo that after noone, they ſailed by the ſhore (determining to la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d) to the Cape de Loupes
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:20324:14"/>
Gonſalues, and ſo to come againe on the South ſide of Saint Thomas, for that the roade was on the South ſide, but they could hardly ſayle from the North ſide, becauſe of the calme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vnder the land.</p>
            <p>The 24. of September, they diſcryed the land called <hi>Iſola de Prince,</hi> diſtant Northeaſt.</p>
            <p>The 25. of Septe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, the aire being very thick and darke, as if ſome great tempeſt would haue followed, as the aire vſeth to be ſo darke about the line, which neuer could be found other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by any ſayler: but where they perceiue a darke cloude in the aire, preſently they take in all their ſayles, for that there commeth a ſodaine and terrible blaſt of wind, thundering and lightning, which continueth for the ſpace of 2. or 3. houres, and by ſaylers is called Trauades: which gone, it is preſently faire weather again: but God be thanked, they had all faire weather, not hauing any Trauades all the way vnto the Cape.</p>
            <p>The 27. of September, all the Captaines went aboord the Admirall, who gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their charge to follow him, if the next day they might land in the Iſland of Saint Thomas.</p>
            <p>The 30. of September, all the Captaines were againe called aboord the Admirall, to appoynt good order to be holden be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on land: halfe that day they ſayled before the wind, that they might reach the ſloweſt ſhips, and the ſame day there was ſuch a number of fiſhes about the Admirals ſhip, that no man could number them, whereby they tooke them in with baskets, being as bigge as Smelts, and after them followed 2. or 3. hundred great fiſhes to deuoure them: whereby there roſe ſuch a noyſe in the water, as if it had beene a tempeſt: yet was the weather very faire and calme: but there ordinarily the ſea is ful of fiſh. One of the ſaylers had hanged a paire of bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ouer-boord for the ſpace of an houre, and when hee drew them vp againe, he found in them at the leaſt 700. fiſhes. The ſame day as diuers boates lay on boord the Admirall, one of them had the rother broken off by a fiſh, &amp; diuers of the fiſhes leapt into the boates.</p>
            <p>The firſt of October at noone, they were about a mile from
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:20324:14"/>
the land, that is, three miles, ſayling from the Cape of <hi>Loupes Gonſalues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third of October they ſayled with a good gale of winde.</p>
            <p>The fift of October in the morning, they ſet ſayle, and by night lay vnder the land. The ſame day they let a prize driue vpon the ſea, hauing ſet it on fire, but firſt vnlade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al her goods.</p>
            <p>The ſixt of October they ſayled with a South-wind.</p>
            <p>The tenth of October they ankered vnder the land, hard by the Cape, where they found a ſhip of Amſterdam, beeing the ſhip which they before had diſcried.</p>
            <p>The ſame day the Admirall ſent his pinnace to a riuer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout foure miles from the Cape <hi>de Loupes Gonſalues,</hi> for freſh water, where they ſayled about foure miles vp into the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: whereon there ſtood a great village, which with their pinnace they could not approach, by reaſon that the trees ſtood ſo thicke vpon the ſhore: and as the Pinnace ſayled forward, great numbers of Monkies leaped in, and about it; at the laſt they ſhotte off a musket, whereupon preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there came diuers wilde men in Cannoes of ſixe foote long that brought them (hauing a little Iron and linnen-cloth which they had taken with them, to prouide ſome fruite, egges, and fleſh for the Admirall) to the village, where they found a companie of wilde men ſtanding with their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, the Captaine hauing a ruſtie ſword vpon his ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, with an olde cappe vpon his head, which brought them preſently into the village, and to their kings houſe, whome they found ſitting making money of mother of Pearle: which money (as they ſayd) he onely vſed when hee meant to buy himſelfe a wife of his enemie, and no man might make ſuch money but hee.</p>
            <p>The Hollanders beeing there, the King preſently layde downe his tooles, and ſate ſtill in his ſeate verie ſtoutly, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their maner, hauing a long beard with diuers rings, paynted about his armes, and about his eyes of diuers co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, with a hatte vpon his head, beeing all ſtucke round
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:20324:15"/>
about with great pinnes, in maner of a crown, in ſuch ſort, that at the firſt the Hollanders were abaſhed, for that hee ſeemed like a diuell: behind him ſat two of his wiues, the one all black, the other all red painted, and were naked, onely that they had certaine cloathes about their priuities.</p>
            <p>Now the Hollanders ſtanding before the King, the King ſpake fiue wordes one before the other: which words both they, and all the wilde men that were preſent, muſt ſpeake af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him: but the Hollanders vnderſtood not what they meant: and when the words were ended, they all together clapt their hands; whereupon the Hollanders had free libertie to goe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the village to bartle and buy what they would.</p>
            <p>They brought ſome of the Hollanders into their Temple, where they perceiued a very old blacke leane man, with a gray beard, ſitting as ſtill as if hee had beene dead, at whoſe feete the wilde men fell downe, for they held him for a great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet: it is to be ſuppoſed that hee was a ſouth-ſayer, and that hee dealt with the diuell, for there they knew not what God is: when it lighteneth &amp; thu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dereth, as there it doth very ſore &amp; often, then they pray vnto their Prophet that it may ceaſe: for their opinion is, that as then the diuel tempteth them, and that hee is ſuppoſed to bee a South-ſayer: the reaſon was, for that one of the Hollanders had loſt a peece of linnen, about tenne elles long, which ſome of the wilde men had ſtolen from him, &amp; there was one of the wilde men that could ſpeak Portingall, that as the Hollanders were going out of the village, ſhewed them thereof, and went and ſhewed the Captaine: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Captain went preſently backe again into the village, &amp; to the temple, where he vnderſtood who had ſtolen it, ſo that he brought the peece of linnen to them againe.</p>
            <p>In the village you ſhall not finde any handi-crafts men, but onely two Smithes, which made nothing elſe, but heades for pikes and darts, for there the wilde men make great warres againſt their neighbours: euerie ſeuen or eight miles they haue a king, by the parting of certaine riuers within the land.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:20324:15"/>The women of this village ſeeme to be very deſirous of the company of white men, as it appeared at the Hollanders departure from them, by a Gentelman, called <hi>Lanſcroen,</hi> who being compaſſed about by many of the women, euery one ſought to haue their wil of him: but he not being willing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, got away from them.</p>
            <p>The 17. of October in the morning, they ſaw the Iſland of <hi>S. Thomas</hi> being Northweſt from them, all that day with little ſayle, holding Northweſt, they compaſſed about, the better to know the land.</p>
            <p>The 19. of October in the morning, being arriued in the road of <hi>S. Thomas,</hi> preſently the Generall landed, with all their ſouldiers, and at their landing found no reſiſtance: &amp; ſo march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing orderly towards the towne, they met a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of men co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from the towne, who for the ſpace of an hower ſhot at them, but the Hollanders loſt not aboue 2. or 3. men: which done, they marched forward, and they of the towne fled into the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taines, ſo that the Hollanders were preſently maſters of the towne, and at their pleaſures laded the goods which they found there, into their ſhippes.</p>
            <p>The ſame day, <hi>Ellert de Ionghe,</hi> Captaine of the artillery for the viage, in the name of Graue Maurice, the ſtates of Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, &amp; the General, ſummoned the caſtell to yeeld, their liues ſaued, but they refuſed the condition: whereupon the ſaid <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lert</hi> was by the ſaid Generall ſent againe, to will them to yeeld vp the caſtle vpon the aforeſaid conditions, or if they refuſed, &amp; would ſtay the pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting of ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce (which was ready) before it, that then they ſhould expect nothing but death. Which they againe denied: ſaying, that they had take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an oth vnto the King, ſo that they could not ſo lightly yeeld vp ſuch a caſtle.</p>
            <p>The ſame night the battery was prepared, and by day two peeces of ordinance were planted, which they of the caſtle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuing, in the morning put forth an Enſigne of peace, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that two of their men might ſpeake with the Generall to agree with him about the deliuery of the caſtle, which was graunted them, each party meeting: meane time the Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:20324:16"/>
placed ſeuen peeces to batter it.</p>
            <p>The 21. of Octob. in the morning, by agreement made, the caſtle was yeelded vp, the men that were in it being priſoners, vpon condition that they ſhould be ranſomed, euery man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his ability.</p>
            <p>The 22. of October, 200. men being ſent to the ſecond ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle about an houres going from the towne, on the North ſide, they within the caſtle being afraid, fled and forſooke it, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they found three braſſe peeces, which caſtle they preſently manned, and at their departure threw it downe.</p>
            <p>The 23. of Octob. the captaine of the Artillery &amp; captaine <hi>Loe,</hi> were appointed to march into the Iſland, who riding vpon two horſes ſent them by the enemy, preſently ſet forward, for it was the enemies deſire, and in their places two of the enemy remained as pledges: and being in the land they found a troupe of about 600. men all naked, with peeces on their ſhoulders, except about 40. Portingales that were among them, who notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding ſhewed to be very weake of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion. In this Iſland are many ſlaues, ſome of the Portin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gales haue 150. and he is but a meane man, that hath not at the leaſt 3. or 400. ſlaues.</p>
            <p>The ſame day they departed, &amp; it was on both ſides agreed, that the next day they ſhould meet againe.</p>
            <p>The 24. of October, the ſaid captaines went againe into the Iſland, hauing aduertiſed the Generall what they had done, &amp; within 3. houres after returning againe to make report vnto the Generall of their proceedings, they found him dead: for that when they ſpake with him before, his ſicknes was no other but a kind of weaknes, which had continued two daies, yet did he not leaue walking and ſtanding: whereupon hee cauſed himſelfe to be let bloud in the arme, which being done, &amp; fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling himſelfe very weake, ſaid vnto thoſe that were preſent by him, This ſicknes taketh me very ſore: &amp; ſo laid him downe in his clothes vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his bed, where he had not layne long, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently being ſtriken with death, without vttering any words he died. The ſame euening, certaine of the Captaines put him
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:20324:16"/>
in a coffin, and gaue it out, that the Generals body ſhould be throwne into the Sea, becauſe it ſhould not be knowne by the enemy where they meant to bury him: wherupon he was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently conueyed into a boate, &amp; ſo rowed from the land, and about midnight brought againe to land: where being ariued, without any noiſe they buried him in a houſe within the towne of <hi>S. Thomas,</hi> which houſe after that, with all the houſes about it was burnt to aſhes.</p>
            <p>Touching the ranſoming of the caſtles, the towne and Churches were not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehended therein, for that their higheſt offer was not aboue 10. thouſand Duckets.</p>
            <p>The 25. of October, they made a trench within the towne.</p>
            <p>The 27. of Octob. the peeces appointed for battery being brought thither, preſently they lodged their me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the trench.</p>
            <p>The 28. of October, in the euening the Spaniards ſet the towne on fire in three places.</p>
            <p>The 3. of Nouember, the Hollanders iſſued out of the town onely to ſet the country on fire.</p>
            <p>The 4. of Nouember, they ſhipped their men, and ſet all the towne on fire.</p>
            <p>The great ordinance that they found in the firſt caſtle were 21. braſſe peeces great and ſmall.</p>
            <p>Firſt, two Double cannons, each waighing 10000. pound, their bullet being 57. pound.</p>
            <p>Ten braſſe peeces waighing one with the other 3300. li.</p>
            <p>Nine baſſes of braſſe being moſt of them red copper.</p>
            <p>There was likewiſe 3. baſſes of braſſe, and certaine yron peeces found in the towne.</p>
            <p>The goods in the towne were certaine thouſand cheſts of ſuger, and a great number of very great Elephants teeth, very much wool and ſilkes, with other wares, &amp; many other things, with all the belles.</p>
            <p>Alſo in the road they found 2. ſhips ful laden with ſuger, ech of them being of 180. tunnes: in one of the ſhips there was a broken peece of ordinance of 10000. li. waight, red copper, which they meant to haue molten in Lisbon.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:20324:17"/>The 5. of October, they ſet ſaile, all the priſoners of the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle being ranſomed, onely the Gouernour of the Iſland, &amp; him they tooke with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: which done, they made towards the cape <hi>de Loupes Gonſalues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 7. of Octob. captaine <hi>Cloyer</hi> died, being Vice Admiral.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="description">
                        <head>The deſcription of the Iſland of S. Thomas.</head>
                        <p>THe Iſland of <hi>S. Thomas,</hi> is an Iſland lying right vnder the <hi>Equinoctial</hi> line, almoſt round, and in compaſſe 15. Dutch miles. In the middle of this Iſland ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth a great hill, compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed about with many trees, aboue, &amp; betweene the which trees there is continually a dropping clowd, which yeeldeth ſo much water, that it maketh all the land about to continew moiſt, and very apt to bring foorth ſuger, by which meanes the whole Iſland abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth ſo much in ſuger: the Iſland is moſt inhabited by Moores that gather &amp; dreſſe the ſuger: in it there is but one ſmall towne called <hi>Poroaſan.</hi> The ayre is very vnwholeſome, wherby ſuch ſtrangers or their iſſues, as dwell or come thither, commonly euery 8. daies are troubled with an ague, and loſe many of their men. In it there groweth not any corne, nor wine: the principall meate of the inhabitants is a roote called <hi>Ignamo,</hi> their drinke being water or wine of Palme trees: in this Iſland are many trees, but fewe that beare fruit, they haue many birds of diuers colours, and ſome ſtraunge beaſts, as muskcats, and in the ſea an innumerable number of Whales.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>The 8. of October, brother <hi>Ianſen</hi> was choſen Vice Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall.</p>
            <p>The 29. of October, in the morning, an aſſembly was made in the fleet, and it was determined among them, preſently to ſayle homeward, for that in the ſpace of two dayes, that they had ſayled from <hi>S. Thomas,</hi> there died in their ſhippes about 1032. or 33. men, and had aboue 1000. more ſicke, in ſuch maner, that they could hardly rule their ſhips, being as then one degree Southward from the lyne, and from <hi>S. Thomas</hi> Weſtward 180. miles, holding their courſe Northweſt.</p>
            <p>The 30. of October, they draue with a calme vpon the Sea: then the Captaines of the ſhips agreed, that 6. of their ſhippes
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:20324:17"/>
ſhould ſaile towards Braſilia, to ſee if they could fetch any ſhips from thence: the ſhips appointed were captaine Broer of Memelike, Admirall, captaine Leefhebber of the Maze, cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Cat of Horne, captaine Hart of the Maze, captaine Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Iohn Coxe, captaine Andreas of the Maze, the Pinnace of Peter Verdoes of the Maze, which ſhips the ſame day de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted.</p>
            <p>The 7. of Noue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, the fleet not being able to paſſe by the ſalt Iſlands, becauſe they lay too farre Northward from them, they were conſtrayned to ſaile almoſt to the Flemiſh Iſlands, hauing as then the ſunne at 13. degrees.</p>
            <p>The ſame euening, as ſome of them ſat eating in their ſhip, the captaine asked if they ſhould haue any freſh fiſh that night? anſwere was made, no: but preſently God ſent them a flying fiſh aboord, and fell cloſe by them as they ſat at meat, being as great as a common Haddock: and becauſe God ſent them the fiſh ſo miraculouſly, therefore they commaunded the cooke preſently to broyle it: and before it was waſht &amp; made cleane, God ſent them an other, which fell againſt a ſtoole as they ſat at the table.</p>
            <p>The 16. of Nouember, the captaines aſſembled, the ſhippes bearing to Leeward.</p>
            <p>The 20. of Nouember, in the morning betimes they diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered a ſtrange ſhip, but could not ouertake it, being the firſt ſayle that they had ſeene in their returne homeward, the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther being ſtill and cleere.</p>
            <p>The 20. of Nouember, they held to Leeward, to ſtay for 11. of their ſhippes, thinking they were behind, but could not heare any newes of them.</p>
            <p>The 23. of Nouember, in the morning, being 25. ſhippes together, the wind began to riſe high and higher.</p>
            <p>The 24. of Nouember in the morning, they were but foure ſhips in company.</p>
            <p>The fiue and twentieth day of Nouember, they ſayled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the wind, after three ſhips that lay to Leeward from
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20324:18"/>
them, being of their owne company.</p>
            <p>The 31. of December, they were 5. ſhips in company.</p>
            <p>The firſt of February, the ſhip wherein captaine <hi>Ellert de Ionghe</hi> was, found it ſelfe alone without company, and ſo conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed til the 6. of February, when it found an Engliſhma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that had taken a barke, wherein they were, for that their owne ſhip was ſuncke, which Engliſhman for the ſpace of ſixe dayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, had had no drinke, ſo that the Hollander gaue them both water and wine.</p>
            <p>The tenth day the ſhip draue in great danger to be loſt, if God had not holpen it.</p>
            <p>The 14. of February, there came to Plimmouth the ſhippe called the Golden Lion, wherein died III. men. Eight daies after, the Orange tree, being the Generals ſhip, arriued there, hauing caſt 120. of 150. men ouerboord that died in her, and in the ſhip were but 6. ſound men, the reſt ſicke.</p>
            <p>Being in England, the Lion and the Orange tree tooke in freſh men.</p>
            <p>The 1. of March, the ſhip that was left alone, went to ſea, and the 9. of the ſame moneth it arriued in the Taſſell. And all the ſhippes that came in either before or after it, had but few men, and were in great danger.</p>
            <p>Touching the great death of men that happened among them, was partly that there is a great heat, and an vnwhole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome aire in the Iſland of Saint <hi>Thomas,</hi> becauſe it lieth right vnder the Equinoctiall line, ſo that many of their men died of burning feauers, through the heate of the ſunne, which bred great paine in their heads, ſo that in three or foure dayes they were aliue and dead, which is there called <hi>la Madorre:</hi> for by experience they found in one that died ſodainely, that all the fat in his belly and guts was wholly molten, and lay at the bottome of his belly like water: this cutting of him vp was done, becauſe diuers of their men complained of a pain in their bellies: ſome of them going and ſtanding, without any ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to bee perceiued in them, fell out of their wits, ſo that
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:20324:18"/>
foure men had ſufficient to doe to hold them vntill they died<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> this madneſſe proceeded from the heate of the ſunne, that cauſed the braines in their heads to ſtirre or moue.</p>
            <p>Many died with eating too much of the blacke ſugar, and of the great Palme-tree nuts, which haue much ſweete liquor within them, wherewith they drunke themſelues giddie, and thereby got a looſeneſſe in their bodies, as alſo by the blacke ſugar, whereof preſently inſued the bloudy flix, ſo that many died of that diſeaſe.</p>
            <p>Many alſo ſpoyled themſelues by lying naked vpon the hatches in the night time when the Moone ſhined (to coole the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues) which thereabouts yeldeth a venimous vnwholſome aire, ſpecially when men ſleepe.</p>
            <p>Some vſed the companie of the blacke women, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by many of them loſt their liues: the women being ſo hot of nature, that they are wholly contrarie to the nature of white men, and not to bee eſteemed as naturall heate: let an inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitant therein dwelling haue to do, or accompanie with one of their women, (although ſhe be a white woman) and the next day let himſelfe bloud, hee dyeth without fayle, although he were a King.</p>
            <p>Many alſo died of looſeneſſe in their bodies, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly happeneth by long viages, ſpecially, when they were halfe ſeas ouer, vnder 45. and 46. degrees: for then it was cold, ſuch as were ſick, not being able to endure it: for there they had a ſide winde for the ſpace of fiue weekes, in the which time many of their men died, ſo that they thinke in all, that there died about a thouſand eight hundred men, of looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in their bodies, when they were in the height aforeſaid, being vpon the ſixt of Ianuarie 1600.</p>
            <p>It is not to be maruailed at, that they loſt many men by the ſickneſſes aforeſaid (ſeeing the Portingals themſelues doe the like, being men of hotter conplections then we are, &amp; borne vnder a warmer climate) &amp; by that means haue loſt many me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as <hi>Americus Veſpucius</hi> himſelfe witneſſeth, who not onely
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:20324:19"/>
writeth of the vnwholſome ayre of this Iſland, but alſo ſayth that it is ſtrange, that a man of Europa ſhould be found in that place with gray haires, or beeing aboue fiftie yeeres of age. The Portingales are of opinion, that this ſickneſſe among men of Europa, commeth, becauſe they vſe to drinke often to coole their bodies, and without eating, and ſpecially becauſe there is little winde, whereby the ayre is more infected.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20324:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
